Poor People's Campaign 119
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Poor People's Campaign Collection
1968
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Southern Christian Leadership Conference
119
1 Linear feet
1 Boxes
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence This series contains correspondence concerning activities of the Poor People's Campaign of 1968. Series II: Reports and Statements This series contains congressional reports and internal memorandums regarding the work of the Poor People's Campaign participants. Series III: Publications This series contains newsletters documenting activities at Resurrection City. Series IV: Miscellaneous This series contains brochures, programs, songs, and other items that do not pertain to any other series. Series V: Clippings This series contains newspaper clippings on the Poor People's Campaign, Resurrection City, and the funeral of the late Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
Biographical / Historical
The Poor People's Campaign was a 1968 effort to gain economic and human rights for poor people in the United States. The event was planned by Martin Luther King Jr. and the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, and carried out under the leadership of Ralph Abernathy in the wake of Dr. King's assassination. After participants presented their demands to Congress and President Lyndon Johnson a 3,000 person protest camp known as Resurrection City was constructed on the National Mall. The Campaign began on May 12, when demonstrators led by Coretta Scott King demanded an Economic Bill of Rights. Over the next few weeks nine major caravans of poor people from various cities arrived in the District. Marchers participated in a variety of activities throughout the city culminating in the June 19 Solidarity Day rally. On June 23, the demonstration's permit with the National Park Service expired and some members of Congress called for the immediate removal of the encampment. On June 24 over one thousand police officers arrived to clear the camp of its five hundred remaining residents, many of whom were arrested for refusing to vacate the site.
Custodial History
Various donors.
Scope and Contents
The contents of this collection include: correspondence, flyers, memorabilia, newsletters, newspaper clippings, poems, and songs.
Civil rights; Poor People's Campaign; Demonstrations; Mall, The (Washington, D.C.); Political activists
- Series 1: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence concerning activities of the Poor People's Campaign of 1968.
  - "A Letter to Friends from D.C. Jail", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondent Letter, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter to Judge, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Reports and Statements
  This series contains congressional reports and internal memorandums regarding the work of the Poor People's Campaign participants.
  - A Report to Baltimore Yearly Meeting of Friends, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Legislative Committee for the Poor People's Campaign, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William Penn Newsletter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Summary of the Commission Report and Legislative before Congress, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Policy Statement on Poverty, Jobs, and Income, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Income Memorandum, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Action Bulletin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Publications
  This series contains newsletters documenting activities at Resurrection City.
  - Newsletter, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - True Unity News of Resurrection City, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 4: Miscellaneous
  This series contains brochures, programs, songs, and other items that do not pertain to any other series.
  - Solidarity Day Programme, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - MLK Slogans, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brochures, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Resurrection City Songs, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - List of Worshipers Arrested on Capitol, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Job Mobilization Support Sheet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - True Unity Resurrection Poems, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Flyer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series 5: Clippings
  This series contains newspaper clippings on the Poor People's Campaign, Resurrection City, and the funeral of the late Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)